MacCrate, Robert; Papers apap026
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Robert McCrate Papers
1959-1962
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
MacCrate, Robert
apap026
5.0 cubic ft. processed to date
Robert MacCrate was a lawyer who served as counsel to New York State Governor Nelson Rockefeller.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Robert MacCrate, on July 7, 1989.
Scope and Contents
This manuscript collection contains retained copies of memoranda (1959-62) sent to Governor Rockefeller by his counsel, Robert MacCrate, concerning pending bills in the New York Senate and Assembly. Bound with the memoranda are copies of the Governor's approval or veto messages for the bills. The memoranda and approval or veto messages are arranged by year and source of the bill (Senate or Assembly), and thereunder by bill number. All bills considered by the legislature are not included in this collection, but the range of subjects in the bills that were considered by MacCrate was quite large including business regulations, court reorganization, education law and zoning regulations. Yearly subject indexes to the Governor's approval and veto messages for both Assembly and Senate bills appear at the end of the last volume for each year.
Administrative History
Robert MacCrate was born in Brooklyn, N.Y., on July 18, 1921. He married Constance Trapp on May 4, 1946, and they had three children: Christopher Robert, Barbara Constance, and Thomas John. MacCrate received a B.A. from Haverford College in 1943, and an LL.B. from Harvard University in 1948. He was accepted to the New York bar in 1949 and to the District of Columbia bar in 1965. He was an associate of the firm Sullivan and Cromwell in New York city from 1948 to 1955, and later he was a partner (1956-59, 1962-present). He was law secretary to New York Appelate Division Presiding Justice David W. Peck (1951), and counsel to New York Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller (1959-62). Under Governor Rockefeller, MacCrate, served as associate counsel (Feb. 2, 1959-June 1, 1959) and then counsel (June 1, 1959-June 30, 1962). The primary responsibility of counsel to the governor was to translate the governor's programs into law. He and his staff ensured that bills were correctly drafted and helped to prevent enactment of bills that were antithetical to the governor's programs. Along with the budget director and the secretary to the governor, the counsel was one of the people on whom Governor Rockefeller relied most heavily for administration and program development. MacCrate later served as special counsel to the U.S. Army investigation into the Mylai incident (1969-70), counsel of the New York State Court on Judiciary (1971), and President of the American Bar Association (1987-89). During his career, he contributed articles to professional journals.
MacCrate died in April 2016 at age 94. He was survived by his three children, their spouses, 10 grandchildren and seven great-grandchildren. His wife prceded him in death earlier that year.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically. There are no series.
Public Servants; Legislature; New York (State)--Social conditions; Legislature; MacCrate, Robert
- Assembly Bills, 1-2999, 1959 (Box 1 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 1)
- Assembly Bills, 3000-end, 1959 (Box 1 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 2)
- Senate Bills, 1-2499, 1959 (Box 1 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 3)
- Senate Bills, 2500-end, 1959 (Box 1 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 4)
- Assembly Bills, 1-2999, 1960 (Box 2 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 1)
- Assembly Bills, 3000-end, 1960 (Box 2 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 2)
- Senate Bills, 1-2999, 1960 (Box 2 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 3)
- Senate Bills, 3000-end, 1960 (Box 3 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 1)
- Assembly Bills, 1-2999, 1961 (Box 3 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 2)
- Assembly Bills, 3000-end, 1961 (Box 3 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 3)
- Senate Bills,1-2499, 1961 (Box 4 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 1)
- Senate Bills, 2500-end, 1961 (Box 4 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 2)
- Assembly Bills,1-3299, 1962 (Box 4 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 3)
- Assembly Bills, 3300-end, 1961 (Box 5 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 1)
- Senate Bills, 1-2699, 1962 (Box 5 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 2)
- Senate Bills, 2700-end, 1962 (Box 5 (Robert McCrate Papers), Folder 3)